<chapter name="Process Properties">

<h2>Process Properties</h2>

Here is collected some possibilities to affect the generation of 
all internally implemented processes in one go, or some coherent
subset thereof. Phase space cuts appear on a special page.

<h3>Incoming partons</h3>

<code>InFlux</code> is base class for the combination of allowed incoming 
partons in a given process, and keeps track of parton densities and 
common weight factors (such as charge) required to give the process 
cross section.

<p/>
There is one useful degree of freedom in this class:
<modeopen name="InFlux:nQuark" default="5" min="0" max="5">
Number of allowed incoming quark flavours in the beams; a change 
to 4 would thus exclude <ei>b</ei> and <ei>bbar</ei> as incoming 
partons, etc.
</modeopen>

<p/>
There is also the possibility to obtain some documentation.
<flag name="InFlux:showChannels" default="off">
At initialization show which incoming flavours and flavour combinations
have beeen set up, process by process, along with initial weight 
(e.g. charges or CKM factors) assigned to each of them.
</flag>

<h3>Generic cross sections</h3>

<code>SigmaProcess</code> is base class for all hard processes 
implemented in PYTHIA 8. For <ei>2 -> 1</ei> processes it 
should give <ei>sigmaHat(sHat)</ei>, for <ei>2 -> 2</ei> ones 
<ei>d(sigmaHat(sHat, tHat))/d(tHat)</ei>.

The size of QCD cross sections is mainly determined by 
<parm name="SigmaProcess:alphaSvalue" default="0.1265" 
min="0.06" max="0.25">
The <ei>alpha_strong</ei> value at scale <ei>M_Z^2</ei>. 
</parm>

<p/>
The actual value is then regulated by the running to the scale 
<ei>Q^2</ei>, at which <ei>alpha_strong</ei> is evaluated

<modepick name="SigmaProcess:alphaSorder" default="1" min="0" max="2">
Order at which <ei>alpha_strong</ei> runs,
<option value="0">zeroth order, i.e. <ei>alpha_strong</ei> is kept 
fixed.</option>
<option value="1">first order, which is the normal value.</option>
<option value="2">second order. Since other parts of the code do 
not go to second order there is no strong reason to use this option, 
but there is also nothing wrong with it.</option>
</modepick>

<p/>
QED interactions are regulated by the <ei>alpha_electromagnetic</ei>
value at the <ei>pT^2</ei> scale of an interaction.
 
<modepick name="SigmaProcess:alphaEMorder" default="1" min="-1" max="1">
The running of <ei>alpha_em</ei> used in hard processes.
<option value="1">first-order running, constrained to agree with
<code>StandardModel:alphaEMmZ</code> at the <ei>Z^0</ei> mass.
</option>
<option value="0">zeroth order, i.e. <ei>alpha_em</ei> is kept 
fixed at its value at vanishing momentum transfer.</option>
<option value="-1">zeroth order, i.e. <ei>alpha_em</ei> is kept 
fixed, but at <code>StandardModel:alphaEMmZ</code>, i.e. its value
at the <ei>Z^0</ei> mass.
</option> 
</modepick>

<h3>Special cross sections</h3>

Here settings that affect some special group of processes, but not all.

<modeopen name="SigmaProcess:nQuark" default="3" min="0" max="5">
Number of allowed outgoing new quark flavours in 
<ei>q qbar -> q' qbar'</ei> and <ei>g g-> q qbar</ei> processes, 
where quarks are treated as massless in the matrix-element expressions 
(but correctly in the phase space). It is thus assumed that <ei>c cbar</ei> 
and <ei>b bbar</ei> are added separately with masses taken into account. 
A change to 4 would also include <ei>c cbar</ei> in the massless 
approximation, etc. 
</modeopen>

<modeopen name="SigmaProcess:nQuarkInLoop" default="5" min="3" max="6">
Number of quark flavours included in the box graphs resposible for 
<ei>g g -> g gamma</ei> and <ei>g g-> gamma gamma</ei> processes.
Owing to the complexity if the massive expressions, quarks are treated 
as massless. The default value should be applicable in the range of 
transverse momenta above the <ei>b</ei> mass but below the <ei>t</ei> one.
</modeopen>

<modepick name="SigmaProcess:gmZmode" default="0" min="0" max="2">
Choice of full <ei>gamma^*/Z^0</ei> structure or not in relevant 
processes.
<option value="0">full <ei>gamma^*/Z^0</ei> structure,
with interference included.</option>
<option value="1">only pure <ei>gamma^*</ei> contribution.</option>
<option value="2">only pure <ei>Z^0</ei> contribution.</option>
</modepick>

</chapter>

<!-- Copyright C 2007 Torbjorn Sjostrand -->
