<chapter name="Event Information">

<h1>Event Information</h1>

The <ci>Info</ci> class collects various one-of-a-kind information, 
some relevant for all events and others for the current event. 
An object <ci>info</ci> is a public member of the <ci>Pythia</ci>
class, so if you e.g. have declared <ci>Pythia pythia</ci>, the
<ci>Info</ci> methods can be accessed by 
<ci>pythia.info.method()</ci>. Most of this is information that 
could also be obtained e.g. from the event record, but is here more
directly available. It is intended for processes generated internally
in Pythia8, not for ones read in e.g. via the Les Houches Accord.

Here are the currently available methods:
<method name="list()">
a listing of most of the information set for the current event. 
</method>
<method name="idA(), idB()">
the identities of the two beam particles. 
</method>
<method name="pzA(), pzB()"> 
the longitudinal momenta of the two beam particles.
</method>
<method name="eA(), eB()"> 
the energies of the two beam particles.
</method>
<method name="mA(), mB()"> 
the masses of the two beam particles.
</method>
<method name="eCM(), s()"> 
the cm energy and its square for the two beams. 
</method>
<method name="name(), code()"> 
the name and code of the subprocess that occured.
</method>
<method name="nFinal()"> 
the number of final-state partons in the hard subprocess.
</method>
<method name="isResolved()"> 
are beam particles resolved, i.e. were PDF's used for the subprocess?
</method>
<method name="isDiffractiveA(), isDiffractiveB()"> 
is either beam diffractively excited?
</method>
<method name="id1(), id2()"> 
the identities of the two partons coming in to the hard subprocess.
</method>
<method name="x1(), x2()"> 
<ei>x</ei> fractions of the two partons coming in to the hard subprocess.
</method>
<method name="pdf1(), pdf2()"> 
parton densities <ei>x*f(x,Q^2</ei> )evaluated for the two incoming 
partons; could be used e.g. for reweighting purposes. 
</method>
<method name="Q2pdf()"> 
the <ei>Q^2</ei> scale at which the densities were evaluated.
</method>
<method name="mHat(), sHat()">
 the invariant mass and its square for the hard subprocess.
</method>
<method name="tHat(), uHat()"> 
the remaining two Mandelstam variables; only defined for <ei>2 -> 2</ei>
processes. 
<method name="pTHat(), pT2Hat()"> 
transverse momentum and its square in the rest frame of a <ei>2 -> 2</ei>
processes. 
</method>
<method name="m3Hat(), m4Hat()"> 
the masses of the two outgoing particles in a <ei>2 -> 2</ei> processes. 
</method>
<method name="thetaHat(), phiHat()"> 
the polar and azimuthal scattering angles in the rest frame of 
a <ei>2 -> 2</ei> process.
</method>

</chapter>

<!-- Copyright C 2006 Torbjorn Sjostrand -->
