<chapter name="Program Files">

<h2>Program Files</h2>

The code is subdivided into a set of files, mainly by physics 
task. Each file typically contains one main class, but often
with a few related helper classes that are not used elsewhere in 
the program. Normally the files come in pairs.
<ul>
<li>A header file, <code>.h</code> in the <code>include</code> 
subdirectory, where the public interface of the class is declared, 
and inline methods are defined.</li>
<li>A source code file, <code>.cc</code> in the <code>src</code> 
subdirectory, where most of the methods are implemented.</li>
</ul>
During compilation, related dependency files, <code>.d</code>, and 
compiled code, <code>.o</code> are created in the <code>tmp</code>
subdirectory.

<p/>
In part the <code>.xml</code> documentation files in the <code>doc</code>
subdirectory have matching names, but the match is broken by the
desire to group topics more by user interaction than internal 
operation. On these pages the function of the different code files 
is summarized. Currently, each <code>.xml</code> file is also roughly
translated into an <code>.html</code> one, to allow easy viewing of 
the contents in a web browser, but without the interactivity
eventually strived for.

<file name="Pythia"> 
is the main class, that administrates the whole event generation 
process by making use of all the others classes. Objects of most
other classes reside (directly or indirectly) inside <code>Pythia</code>, 
so only a <code>Pythia</code> object needs to be explicitly instantiated 
and addressed   by the user.
</file>

<file name="Event"> 
contains the event record, which basically is a vector of particles.
This file also contains the <code>Particle</code> class, used by 
<code>Event</code>. <code>Pythia</code> uses two <code>Event</code> 
objects, one for the process-level record (<code>process</code>) and 
one for the complete event (<code>event</code>).
</file>

<file name="Information">
is a simple container that gives access to some information on the
nature of the current process, such as Mandelstam variables.
Also contains a small database for errors and warnings encountered 
during program execution.
</file>

<file name="Analysis">
contains routines to analyze events. Currently it can do sphericity 
and cone-jet finding.
</file>

<file name="ProcessLevel">
handles the generation of the (hard) process that sets the character 
of the event. This involves either using internally implemented 
processes  (few so far), using a runtime interface to the Fortran 
PYTHIA 6 process library, or using routines for reading in 
LHA events. 
</file>

<file name="PartonLevel">
turns the (hard) process above into a complete set of partons, by 
adding initial- and final-state radiation, multiple parton--parton
interactions, and beam remnants.
</file>

<file name="HadronLevel">
turns the parton-level event above into a set of outgoing particles,
by applying string fragmentation (with special treatment for low-mass
systems) and secondary decays.
</file>

<file name="ProcessContainer">
packages the information on a given subprocess, combining the 
phase-space selection and cross-section evaluation machineries
with some statistics information. Also sets up the list of processes
to be studied in a run.  
</file>

<file name="SigmaTotal"> 
contains parametrizations of total, elastic and diffractive hadronic 
cross sections.
</file>

<file name="SigmaProcess">
contains the base class and derived classes for the evaluation of
different matrix elements. Will have to be split once a bigger 
number of processes is implemented.
</file>

<file name="InFlux">
keeps track of the allowed combinations of incoming flavours for a
process, and stores the in-state-specific factors in a cross section.
This in particular means the parton densities, but also charges,
CKM matrix elements, and so on.
  
</file>

<file name="PhaseSpace">
selects a point in phase space for the hard-process generation,
optimized to give improved Monte Carlo efficiency.
</file>

<file name="Pythia6">
is an anomaly, namely the ``good old'' Fortran PYTHIA 6.4 program, 
used as the main process library until further notice. Thus there 
is no <code>Pythia6.cc</code> file but instead a <code>Pythia6.f</code> 
one, located in the <code>pythia6</code> subdirectory. The header file 
contains the required wrappers to access the relevant parts of the 
Fortran code from C++.
</file>

<file name="LesHouches">
gives the possibility to feed in parton configurations for the 
subsequent event generation. Two containers are defined, one for 
initialization and one for events, that can be read from 
<code>Pythia</code>. Should be linked to external programs or files.
</file>

<file name="TimeShower"> 
performs timelike final-state transverse-momentum-ordered 
shower evolution.
</file>

<file name="SpaceShower"> 
performs spacelike initial-state transverse-momentum-ordered 
shower evolution.
</file>

<file name="MultipleInteractions"> 
performs multiple parton--parton interactions.
</file>

<file name="Beams"> 
contains information on all partons extracted from the beams.
Defines modified parton distributions accordingly during the
showering and multiple interactions processing, and afterwards
sets up beam remnants.
</file>

<file name="PartonDistributions"> 
contains parton distribution functions for the proton and electron. 
Currently very simple, with only two <ei>p</ei> parametrizations 
available, but it is possible to link in external sets.
</file>

<file name="StringFragmentation"> 
performs string fragmentation of a given set of partons.
</file>

<file name="MiniStringFragmentation"> 
performs string fragmentation in cases where the colour singlet
subsystem mass is so small that one or at most two primary hadrons 
should be produced from it.
</file>

<file name="FragmentationFlavZpT">
contains the classes for describing the fragmentation steps in
flavour and in longitudinal and transverse momentum.
</file>

<file name="FragmentationSystems">
defines some containers of parton systems, for use in 
the fragmentation routines.
</file>

<file name="ParticleDecays">
performs the decays of all normal unstable hadrons and leptons, i.e. 
in mass up to and including <ei>b bbar</ei> systems. It is not 
intended for decays of electroweak resonances, like <ei>Z^0</ei>.  
</file>

<file name="StandardModel"> 
contains the running <ei>alpha_strong</ei>, with <ei>Lambda</ei> 
matching at flavour thresholds, and also a few other parameters 
such as <ei>alpha_em</ei> and <ei>sin^2(theta_W)</ei>.
</file>

<file name="Settings"> 
contains a database of all flags, modes and parameters that determine 
the performance of the generator. Initial values are set from the 
contents of the <code>xml</code> files, but these values can then 
be changed by the user.
</file>

<file name="ParticleData">
contains a database of all necessary particle data (masses, names, ..)
and decay channels.
</file>

<file name="Basics">
contains some basic facilities of general use: a random number
generator <code>Rndm</code>, a four-vector class <code>Vec4</code>, and a 
histogram class <code>Hist</code>.  
</file>

<file name="PythiaStdlib">
is only a <code>.h</code> file, containing all the <code>Stdlib</code> 
headers used in Pythia 8, with <code>using</code> directives. Also 
inlines <code>pow2(x)</code> - <code>pow5(x)</code> for fast powers of 
small integers, <code>sqrtpos(x)</code> to avoid that roundoff gives the 
square root of a negative number, and <code>tolower(string)</code> for 
producing a lowercase string.
</file>

</chapter>

<!-- Copyright C 2006 Torbjorn Sjostrand -->
