<chapter name="Flavour Selection">

<h2>Flavour Selection</h2>

The <code>StringFlav</code> class handles the choice of a new flavour 
in the fragmentation process, and the production of a new hadron 
from a set of input flavours. It is mainly used by the string 
fragmentation machinery (including ministrings), but also e.g.
in some particle decays and for some beam-remnant cases. The basic
concepts are in agreement with <ref>And83</ref>.

<p/>
Currently only simple diquark production of baryons is
included; the more sophisticated popcorn scenario remains to be 
implemented. Therefore the number of parameters on this page will
be expanded later on. 

<h3>New flavours</h3>

The main parameters of the selection of a new flavour are

<parm name="StringFlav:probQQtoQ" default="0.10" min="0.0" max="1.0">
the suppression of diquark production relative to quark production,
i.e. of baryon relative to meson production.
</parm> 

<parm name="StringFlav:probStoU" default="0.30" min="0.0" max="1.0">
the suppression of <ei>s</ei> quark production relative to ordinary 
<ei>u</ei> or <ei>d</ei> one.
</parm> 

<parm name="StringFlav:probSQtoQQ" default="0.4" min="0.0" max="1.0">
the suppression of strange diquark production relative to light
diquark production, over and above the one already given by 
<ei>probStoU</ei>.
</parm> 
 
<parm name="StringFlav:probQQ1toQQ0" default="0.05" 
min="0.0" max="1.0">
the suppression of spin 1 diquark production relative to spin 0 one,
apart from the factor of 3 enhancement of spin 0 from counting the
number of states.
</parm> 

<h3>Meson production</h3>

For a given set of flavours,the main parameters for meson production
are
<parm name="StringFlav:mesonUspin1" default="0.50" min="0." max="1.">
the relative fraction of light (<ei>u</ei>, <ei>d</ei>) mesons that are 
chosen to have spin 1, i.e. be vectors, with the remainder having spin 0, 
i.e. pseudoscalars. 
</parm> 
<parm name="StringFlav:mesonSspin1" default="0.60" min="0." max="1.">
the relative fraction of strange mesons that are chosen to have spin 1, 
i.e. be vectors, with the remainder having spin 0, i.e. pseudoscalars. 
</parm> 
<parm name="StringFlav:mesonCspin1" default="0.70" min="0." max="1.">
the relative fraction of charm mesons that are chosen to have spin 1, 
i.e. be vectors, with the remainder having spin 0, i.e. pseudoscalars. 
</parm> 
<parm name="StringFlav:mesonBspin1" default="0.75" min="0." max="1.">
the relative fraction of bottom mesons that are chosen to have spin 1, 
i.e. be vectors, with the remainder having spin 0, i.e. pseudoscalars. 
</parm> 

<p/>
Inside each light-quark meson nonet, an octet-singlet mixing angle
describes the mixing of the two flavour-diagonal isoscalar = 0 states.
(For terminology and details see <ref>Eid04</ref>, chapter 14 on the 
quark model.)
This angle is needed to specify the probability for such a <ei>q qbar</ei> 
state to project onto a specific meson. More transparent formuale are 
obtained by introducing the angle <ei>alpha = theta + 54.7</ei> degrees:
<eq>
   f  = (uubar + ddbar)/sqrt(2) * sin(alpha) + ssbar * cos(alpha)<br/>  
   f' = (uubar + ddbar)/sqrt(2) * cos(alpha) - ssbar * sin(alpha)
</eq>

<parm name="StringFlav:thetaPS" default="-15." min="-90." max="90.">
gives the mixing angle <ei>theta_PS</ei> in the pseudoscalar meson sector
(which is rather poorly determined), expressed in degrees.
Here <ei>f</ei> is associated with <ei>eta'</ei> and <ei>f'</ei> with 
<ei>eta</ei>. (This standard but counterintuitive choice is fixed up 
in the code by replacing <ei>alpha -> 90^0 - alpha</ei> so that 
<ei>eta &lt;-> eta'</ei>; relative signs do not matter since we are 
interested in probabilities only.)
</parm> 

<parm name="StringFlav:thetaV" default="36." min="-90." max="90.">
gives the mixing angle <ei>theta_V</ei> in the vector meson sector
(which is somewhat better determined), expressed in degrees.
Here <ei>f</ei> is associated with <ei>omega</ei> and <ei>f'</ei> 
with <ei>phi</ei>.
</parm> 

<p/>
Further, the simple model overestimates the production of <ei>eta</ei> 
and, in particular, <ei>eta'</ei> mesons, which can be rectified by 

<parm name="StringFlav:suppressEta" default="1.0" min="0." max="1.">
the additional suppression of <ei>eta</ei> production, multiplying the 
normal production probability.
</parm> 

<parm name="StringFlav:suppressEtaPrime" default="0.4" min="0." max="1.">
the additional suppression of <ei>eta</ei> production, multiplying the 
normal production probability.
</parm> 

<h3>Baryon production</h3>

The relative rate of baryon production is mainly given by the quark
and diquark production parameters plus SU(6) Clebsch-Gordans. The
only extra modifiable parameter is

<parm name="StringFlav:suppressDecuplet" default="1.0" 
min="0.0" max="1.0">
the suppression, relative to default SU(6) factors, of decuplet 
baryon production.
</parm> 
   
</chapter>

<!-- Copyright C 2006 Torbjorn Sjostrand -->
