<chapter name="Front">

<h1>PYTHIA 8</h1>

<h2>Welcome to PYTHIA - The Lund Monte Carlo!</h2>

<p/>
PYTHIA 8 is still incomplete, and should not be 
used for any production runs. What is offered here is only a snapshot, 
to allow interested users to provide feedback on the basic structure. 
The program is under active development, however, and is intended to 
replace the existing PYTHIA 6 as the official version within a year.

<p/>
Use the left-hand index to navigate in the existing documentation, 
e.g. to learn which flags, modes and parameters can be set by the user.
Also note that there is a separate
<a href="pythia8060.pdf" target="page"><b>Brief Introduction</b></a>
(as a pdf file), 
that offers the best way to get to understand the basic structure of 
PYTHIA 8. The current pages offer the more detailed picture, 
with the corresponding danger of then losing overview.  

<p/>
The complete <b>PYTHIA 6.4 Physics and Manual</b>, published in<br/>
<b>T. Sj&ouml;strand, S. Mrenna and P. Skands, JHEP05 (2006) 026</b>,<br/>
in detail describes the physics (partly) implemented also in 
PYTHIA 8. It therefore is the main reference that you should
quote, whether you use PYTHIA 6 or PYTHIA 8.


<p/>
Main author:<br/> 
Torbj&ouml;rn Sj&ouml;strand<br/> 
CERN/PH, CH-1211 Geneva, Switzerland, and<br/>
Department of Theoretical Physics, Lund University, Lund, Sweden<br/>
phone: + 41 - 22 - 767 82 27<br/>
e-mail: torbjorn@thep.lu.se   

<p/>
Author:<br/> 
Stephen Mrenna<br/> 
Computing Division, Simulations Group<br/> 
Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory<br/>
MS 234, Batavia, IL 60510, USA<br/>
phone: + 1 - 630 - 840 - 2556<br/>
e-mail: mrenna@fnal.gov

<p/>
Author:<br/> 
Peter Skands<br/> 
Theoretical Physics Department<br/>
Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory<br/>
MS 106, Batavia, IL 60510, USA<br/> 
phone: + 1 - 630 - 840 - 2270<br/> 
e-mail: skands@fnal.gov 

<p/>
The program and the documentation is
Copyright &copy; 2007 Torbj&ouml;rn Sj&ouml;strand 
 

</chapter>

<!-- Copyright C 2007 Torbjorn Sjostrand -->
