<chapter name="Histograms">
    
<h1>Histograms</h1>

The <ci>Hist</ci> class gives a simple implementation of 
one-dimensional histograms, useful for quick-and-dirty testing, 
without the need to link to more sophisticated packages. 
A Histogram is declared by a    
<class name="Hist name( title, numberOfBins, xMin, xMax)">
where
<argument name="title"> 
is a string with the title of the histogram at output,
</argument>
<argument name="numberOfBins"> 
is the number of bin the <ei>x</ei> range will be subdivided into, 
</argument>
<argument name="xMin"> 
is the lower edge of the histogram,
</argument>
<argument name="xMax"> 
is the upper edge of the histogram.
</argument>
</class>

<p/>
For instance
<code>
   Hist ZpT( "Z0 pT spectrum", 100, 0., 100.);
</code>
Alternatively you can first declare it and later define it:
<code>
   Hist ZpT;
   ZpT.book( "Z0 pT spectrum", 100, 0., 100.);
</code>

Once declared, its contents can be added by repeated calls to fill
<method name="fill( xValue, weight)">
where
<argument name="xValue">
is the <ei>x</ei> position where the filling should occur, and
</argument>
<argument name="weight" default="1.">
is the amount of weight to be added at this <ei>x</ei> value.
</argument>
</method>

<p/>
For instance
<code>
   ZpT.fill( 22.7, 1.); 
</code>
Since the weight defaults to 1 the last argument could have been 
omitted in this case.   

<p/>
A histogram can be printed by making use of the overloaded &lt;&lt; 
operator, e.g.:
<code>
   cout &lt;&lt; ZpT;
</code>

<p/>
A set of overloaded operators have been defined, so that histograms can 
be added, divided by each other (bin by bin) and so on. Also overloaded 
operations with double real numbers are available, so that e.g. 
histograms easily can be rescaled. Thus one may write e.g.
<code>
  allpT = ZpT + 2. * HpT
</code>
assuming that <ci>allpT</ci>, <ci>ZpT</ci> and <ci>HpT</ci> have been 
booked with the same number of bins and <ei>x</ei> range. That 
responsibility rests on the user; some checks are made for compatibility, 
but not enough to catch all possible mistakes. 

<p/>
Some further possibilities are included, like writing out histogram 
contents as a table, for plotting e.g. with Gnuplot.

</chapter>

<!-- Copyright C 2006 Torbjorn Sjostrand -->
