<chapter name="Partial Generation">

<h1>Partial Generation</h1>

Sometimes it may be convenient to omit certain aspects of the event 
generation chain. This cannot be motivated in a full-blown production
run, but can often be convenient for own understanding and for
debug purposes. The flags on this page allow just that.

<p/>
The event generation is subdivided into three levels: the process
level, the parton level and the hadron level, and flags are grouped
accordingly. 

<h2>Process Level</h2>

The <ci>ProcessLevel</ci> class administrates the initial step of 
the event generation, wherein the basic process is selected. Currently 
this is done either using some of the internal processes, or with 
Les Houches Accord input, or from the Fortran Pythia 6.3 code, the 
latter also using the Les Houches Accord standard.

Since there cannot be any event at all without an initial process,
there is no possibility to switch off this part of the story. It is
possible, however, to stop the generation immediately after the
basic process has been selected:

<flag name="Pythia:afterProcessLevel" default="on">
If off then stop the generation after the hard process has been 
generated, but before the parton-level and hadron-level steps. 
The <ci>process</ci> record is filled, but the <ci>event</ci> 
one is not.
</flag>
 
<h2>PartonLevel</h2>

The <ci>PartonLevel</ci> class administrates the middle step of the 
event generation, i.e. the evolution from an input (hard) process from
<ci>ProcessLevel</ci>, containing a few partons only, to a complete 
parton-level configuration to be handed on to <ci>HadronLevel</ci>. 
This step involves the application of initial- and final-state radiation, 
multiple interactions and the structure of beam remnants.

<p/>
Some parts of the event generation on this level may be switched off
individually: 

<flag name="PartonLevel:MI" default="on">
Master switch for multiple interactions; on/off = true/false.
Further options are found on the Multiple Interactions page.
</flag>

<flag name="PartonLevel:ISR" default="on">
Master switch for initial-state radiation; on/off = true/false.
Further options are found on the Spacelike Showers page.
</flag>

<flag name="PartonLevel:FSRinProcess" default="on">
Master switch for final-state radiation in association with the
hard process itself; on/off = true/false.
Further options are found on the Timelike Showers page.
</flag>

<flag name="PartonLevel:FSRinResonances" default="on">
Master switch for final-state radiation in any resonance decays 
subsequent to the hard process itself; on/off = true/false.
Further options are found on the Timelike Showers page.
</flag>

It is also possible to stop the generation immediately after this step:

<flag name="Pythia:afterPartonLevel" default="on">
If off then stop the generation after the hard process and 
parton-level activity has been generated, but before the 
hadron-level steps.
</flag>


<h2>HadronLevel</h2>

The <ci>HadronLevel</ci> class administrates the final step of the 
event generation, wherein the partonic configuration from 
<ci>PartonLevel</ci> is hadronized, including string fragmentation 
and secondary decays.

<p/>
Most of the code in this class deals with subdividing the partonic
content of the event into separate colour singlets, that can be
treated individually by the string fragmentation machinery. When a
junction and an antijunction are directly connected, it also breaks 
the string between the two, so that the topology can be reduced back 
to two separate one-junction systems, while still preserving the
expected particle flow in the junction-junction string region(s).

<p/>
Some parts of the event generation on this level may be switched off
individually: 

<flag name="HadronLevel:Hadronize" default="on">
Master switch for hadronization; on/off = true/false.
Further options are found on the Fragmentation page.
</flag>

<flag name="HadronLevel:Decay" default="on">
Master switch for decays; on/off = true/false.
Further options are found on the Particle Decays page.
</flag>

</chapter>

<!-- Copyright C 2006 Torbjorn Sjostrand -->
