<chapter name="Total Cross Sections">

<h2>Total Cross Sections</h2>

The <code>SigmaTotal</code> class returns the total, elastic, diffractive 
and nondiffractive cross sections in hadronic collisions, and also the
slopes of the <ei>d(sigma)/dt</ei> distributions. The parametrizations 
used are from <ref>Sch97</ref> which borrows some of the total cross 
sections from <ref>Don92</ref>.

<p/>
The allowed combinations of incoming particles are <ei>p + p</ei>, 
<ei>pbar + p</ei>, <ei>pi+ + p</ei>, <ei>pi- + p</ei>, 
<ei>pi0/rho0 + p</ei>, <ei>phi + p</ei>, <ei>J/psi + p</ei>, 
<ei>rho + rho</ei>, <ei>rho + phi</ei>, <ei>rho + J/psi</ei>, 
<ei>phi + phi</ei>, <ei>phi + J/psi</ei>, <ei>J/psi + J/psi</ei>.   
The strong emphasis on vector mesons is related to the description
of <ei>gamma + p</ei> and <ei>gamma + gamma</ei> interactions in a 
Vector Dominance Model framework (which will not be available for some 
time to come, so this is a bit of overkill).

<h3>Variables</h3>

If the internally implemented cross section parametrizations are not 
satisfactory, it is possible to override the cross section values 
(but currently not the <ei>t</ei> slopes), with 

<flag name="SigmaTotal:setOwn" default="no">
Allow a user to set own cross sections by hand; yes/no = true/false.
</flag>

<p/>
When <code>SigmaTotal:setOwn = yes</code>, the user is expected to set 
values for the corresponding cross sections:

<parameter name="SigmaTotal:sigmaTot" default="80." min="0.">
Total cross section in mb.
</parameter>

<parameter name="SigmaTotal:sigmaEl" default="20." min="0.">
Elastic cross section in mb.
</parameter>

<parameter name="SigmaTotal:sigmaXB" default="8." min="0.">
Single Diffractive cross section <ei>A + B -> X + B</ei> in mb.
</parameter>

<parameter name="SigmaTotal:sigmaAX" default="8." min="0.">
Single Diffractive cross section <ei>A + B -> A + X</ei> in mb.
</parameter>

<parameter name="SigmaTotal:sigmaXX" default="4." min="0.">
Double Diffractive cross section <ei>A + B -> X_1 + X_2</ei> in mb.
</parameter>

<p/>
Note that the total cross section subtracted by the elastic and various 
diffractive ones gives the inelastic nondiffractive cross section, 
which therefore is not set separately. If this cross section evaluates 
to be negative the internal parametrizations are used instead of the 
ones here. However, since the nondiffractive inelastic cross section 
is what makes up the minimum-bias event class, and plays a major role 
in the description of multiple interactions, it is important that a 
consistent set is used. 

</chapter>

<!-- Copyright C 2006 Torbjorn Sjostrand -->
