<chapter name="Timelike Showers">
    
<h2>Timelike Showers</h2>

The PYTHIA algorithm for timelike final-state showers is based on
the recent article [1], where a transverse-momentum-ordered
evolution scheme is introduced. This algorithm is influenced by
the previous mass-ordered algorithm in PYTHIA [2] and by the 
dipole-emission formulation in Ariadne [3]. From the mass-ordered
algorithm it inherits a merging procedure for first-order 
gluon-emission matrix elements in essentially all two-body decays 
in the standard model and its minimal supersymmetric extension [4]. 

<p/>
The normal user is not expected to call <code>TimeShower</code> directly, 
but only have it called from <code>Pythia</code>. Some of the parameters 
below, in particular <code>TimeShower:alphaSvalue</code>, would be of 
interest for a tuning exercise, however. 

<h3>Main variables</h3>

The amount of QCD radiation in the shower is determined by 
<parameter name="TimeShower:alphaSvalue" default="0.1265" 
min="0.06" max="0.25">
The <ei>alpha_strong</ei> value at scale <ei>M_Z^2</ei>. The default 
value corresponds to the one tuned to LEP data (using a first-order 
running), so should be taken rather seriously [5].
</parameter>

<p/>
The actual value is then regulated by the running to the scale 
<ei>pT^2</ei>, at which the shower evaluates <ei>alpha_strong</ei>

<mode name="TimeShower:alphaSorder" default="1" min="0" max="2">
Order at which <ei>alpha_strong</ei> runs,
<option value="0">zeroth order, i.e. <ei>alpha_strong</ei> is kept 
fixed.</option>
<option value="1">first order, which is the normal value.</option>
<option value="2">second order. Since other parts of the code do 
not go to second order there is no strong reason to use this option, 
but there is also nothing wrong with it.</option>
</mode>

<p/>
QED radiation is currently regulated by 
<code>StandardModel:alphaEMfix</code>,
since no QED running is implemented in the shower.

<p/>
The rate of radiation if divergent in the <ei>pT -> 0</ei> limit. Here, 
however, perturbation theory is expected to break down. Therefore an 
effective <ei>pT_min</ei> cutoff parameter is introduced, below which 
no emissions are allowed. The cutoff may be different for QCD and QED 
radiation off quarks, and is mainly a technical parameter for QED 
radiation off leptons.

<parameter name="TimeShower:pTmin" default="0.5" min="0.1" max="2.0">
Parton shower cut-off <ei>pT</ei> for QCD emissions.
</parameter>

<parameter name="TimeShower:pTminChgQ" default="0.5" min="0.1" max="2.0">
Parton shower cut-off <ei>pT</ei> for photon coupling to coloured particle.
</parameter>

<parameter name="TimeShower:pTminChgL" default="0.0005" min="0.0001" 
max="2.0">
Parton shower cut-off <ei>pT</ei> for pure QED branchings. 
Assumed smaller than (or equal to) <code>pTminChgQ</code>.
</parameter>

<h3>Further variables</h3>

These should normally not be touched. Their only function is for
cross-checks.

<p/>
There are three flags you can use to switch on or off selected
branchings in the shower: 

<flag name="TimeShower:QCDshower" default="on">
Allow a QCD shower, i.e. branchings <ei>q -> q g</ei>, <ei>g -> g g</ei> 
and <ei>g -> q qbar</ei>; on/off = true/false.
</flag>

<flag name="TimeShower:QEDshowerByQ" default="on">
Allow quarks to radiate photons, i.e. branchings <ei>q -> q gamma</ei>; 
on/off = true/false.
</flag>

<flag name="TimeShower:QEDshowerByL" default="on">
Allow leptons to radiate photons, i.e. branchings l -> l gamma;  
on/off = true/false.
</flag>

<p/>
There are three further possibilities to simplify the shower:

<flag name="TimeShower:MEcorrections" default="on">
Use of matrix element corrections; on/off = true/false.
</flag>

<flag name="TimeShower:phiPolAsym" default="on">
Azimuthal asymmetry induced by gluon polarization; on/off = true/false.
</flag>

<mode name="TimeShower:nQuark" default="5" min="0" max="5">
Number of allowed quark flavours in <ei>g -> q qbar</ei> branchings
(phase space permitting). A change to 4 would exclude 
<ei>g -> b bbar</ei>, etc. 
</mode>

<h3>References</h3>

<ol>
<li>T. Sjostrand and P.Z. Skands, Eur. Phys. J. C39 (2005) 129</li>
<li>M. Bengtsson and T. Sjostrand, Nucl. Phys. B289 (1987) 810</li>
<li>G. Gustafson, Phys. Lett. B175 (1986) 453;
<br/>G. Gustafson and U. Pettersson, Nucl. Phys. B306 (1988) 746;
<br/>L. Lonnblad, Computer Physics Commun. 71 (1992) 15</li>
<li>E. Norrbin and T. Sjostrand, Nucl. Phys. B603 (2001) 297</li>
<li>G. Rudolph, private communication</li>
</ol>

</chapter>

<!-- Copyright C 2006 Torbjorn Sjostrand -->
